As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we truly love the Bible.
わたしたちはエホバの証人として
聖書を本当に大切にしています
Why?
なぜですか？
Because we know it is God’s Word.
聖書は神の言葉だからです
That’s why we love reading it,
we love studying it,
それゆえ聖書を読み 学び
その歴史を喜んで調べるのです
and we love learning about its history.
When we pause
for a moment and reflect on
少し立ち止まって—
過去幾世紀にもわたってなされて来た
聖書を妨害し—
the many efforts that have been made
through the centuries
その頒布さえも阻止しようとした
多くの試みについて考えると—
to hinder and even stop
the distribution of the Bible,
it becomes obvious
that its Author, Jehovah,
次のことは明らかです
それは その著者である
エホバ神ご自身が—
has been personally involved
in preserving
その貴重な言葉を保存し 知らせることに
関与しておられたということです
and making known
his precious Word.
This is very much
in harmony with the thought
これはイザヤ 40章8節の言葉と
見事に調和しています
in Isaiah 40:8:
“The green grass dries up,
“青草は干からび 花は枯れた”
“the blossom withers,
“しかし わたしたちの神の言葉は
定めのない時に至るまで保つのである”
but the word
of our God endures forever.”
With that in mind,
この点を念頭に置いて—
I’m happy to speak
with you this month
今月はわたしがいつも
心にかけている事柄をお話しします
on a theme
that’s very close to my heart:
主題は
“神の言葉は永久に存続する”です
“The Word of Our God Endures Forever.”
The more we come to appreciate
the value of God’s Word,
わたしたちは神の言葉の価値を
認識すればするほど—
the more we’ll be moved to read it
それをもっと読みたいと
願うようになり—
and, even more important,
to apply it in our lives.
さらに重要なことに それを生活に
当てはめるようになります
エホバ神は人に霊感を与えて—
Jehovah gave us an outstanding gift
when he inspired
ご自分の貴重な言葉を
書き記させたとき—
faithful men
to record his precious Word.
貴重な贈り物を与えてくださいました
It’s through the pages of God’s Word
書き記された神の言葉を通してのみ—
that we learn
just how much God loves us.
わたしたちは神の愛の深さ
について学べるのです
Thus, his Word contains
guidance on how to live.
その言葉は生きていくための
道しるべです
It outlines his purpose
in creating us.
それには 人を創造した目的が
記されています
It gives us his precious promises
for life everlasting
平和と幸福の内に得られる—
永遠の命の貴重な神の約束が
記されています
in peace and happiness.
No wonder the apostle Paul
was inspired to write
使徒パウロが テモテ第二 3章16, 17節で
霊感の下に記したことは当を得ています
at 2 Timothy 3:16, 17:
“All Scripture is inspired of God
“聖書全体は神の霊感を受けたもので—”
“and beneficial for teaching,
for reproving,
“教え 戒め 物事を正し 義にそって
訓育するのに有益です”
“for setting things straight,
for disciplining in righteousness,
“so that the man of God
may be fully competent,
“それは神の人が十分な能力を備え—”
“あらゆる良い業に対して
全く整えられた者となるためです”
completely equipped for every good work.”
Of course, Satan the Devil
does not want people to have access
むろんサタン悪魔は
人々が天の父エホバからの—
to these precious truths
from our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
この貴重な真理に接することを
望んでいません
It’s no surprise
that there have been many obstacles
聖書の入手を困難にする多くの障害が
あったのもうなずけます
to making the Bible available.
While Satan may not have been
directly behind all of these,
サタンが背後でそのすべてを
操っていたわけではないものの—
he certainly
has made use of them.
それらを利用したことは明らかです
What are some
of these obstacles,
どんな障害が どのように
克服されてきたのでしょうか？
and how have they been overcome?
Let’s consider the first obstacle:
最初に言語という
障壁について考えましょう
language barriers.
The first 39 books of the Bible,
旧約聖書とも呼ばれる
聖書の最初の39冊の書は—
which are often called the Old Testament,
were written primarily
in the Hebrew language.
主にヘブライ語で書かれました
These books were known
これらの書はヘブライ語を話す
エホバの僕たちによって知られていました
by Hebrew-speaking servants of Jehovah.
However, as time went on,
しかし 時の経過と共に
とりわけバビロン滅亡後に—
particularly after
the destruction of Babylon,
ユダヤ人の多くは他の国民の中に
自分たちの共同体を作りました
many Jews established communities
in other nations of the earth.
Many of these Jews spoke Greek.
その多くはギリシャ語を話し
もはやヘブライ語を用いなくなりました
They no longer used Hebrew.
That meant that many Jews
no longer had access
それは理解できる言語で
聖書に接することが—
to the Scriptures in a language
they could understand.
もはやできなくなったという意味です
Consider what had happened.
次に何が生じましたか？
As Alexander the Great conquered
アレクサンドロス大王が当時の世界を
次々と征服していった結果—
more and more
of the then-known world,
Greek gradually became
ギリシャ語は徐々にその帝国内で
商業と政治の共通語となっていきました
the common language
of commerce and government
throughout his empire.
If the Bible
was to be understood
ギリシャ語を話す
広大な地域に散在しているユダヤ人や—
by the Jews and by Jewish proselytes
ユダヤ教に改宗した人たちに
聖書が理解されるためには—
who were scattered throughout
this vast Greek-speaking territory,
ギリシャ語に翻訳される
必要がありました
it needed to be translated into Greek.
Beginning in about the year 250 B.C.E.,
西暦前250年ごろから—
ヘブライ語聖書はギリシャ語に
翻訳されるようになりました
the Hebrew Scriptures began
to be translated into Greek.
やがてそのギリシャ語訳は—
In time, that Greek translation
came to be known
セプトゥアギンタ訳
として知られるようになりました
as the Septuagint.
It was widely and frequently used
by the Christians
それは西暦1世紀にギリシャ語を話す
クリスチャンたちによって—
in the first century who spoke Greek.
広く頻繁に用いられました
In fact, the writers
of the Christian Greek Scriptures,
実際 クリスチャン・ギリシャ語聖書
つまり新約聖書の筆者たちは—
which is often called
the New Testament,
frequently quoted directly
from that translation.
その翻訳から頻繁に直接引用しました
このようにしてその障害は
克服されました
So that obstacle had been overcome.
But there were many more
language obstacles ahead.
しかし さらに多くの
言語の障壁がありました
As the Roman Empire
began to flourish,
ローマ帝国が繁栄するようになると—
ギリシャ語に代わってラテン語が
共通語になりました
Latin replaced Greek
as a common language.
Now it was necessary
to translate the Bible into Latin.
今度は 聖書をラテン語に
翻訳する必要が生じました
Some Latin translations
of the Bible books began to appear.
ラテン語の聖書翻訳がいくつか
登場するようになりました
But it was in the year 405 C.E.
that Jerome completed
しかしヒエロニムスがラテン語の
聖書全体の翻訳を完成したのは—
the definitive Latin translation
of the Bible.
西暦405年のことでした
It came to be known
それはラテン語ウルガタ訳として
知られるようになりました
as the Latin Vulgate.
Jerome’s translation
would become
ヒエロニムスの翻訳は
次の千年あまりの期間—
the standard Bible
used by Christendom
キリスト教世界において
標準聖書となりました
for the next nearly 1,000 years.
However, Latin soon became
the language of the learned and the elite,
しかし ラテン語はすぐに
教育のあるエリートの言語となったため—
so the common people
could no longer understand
一般の人々は聖書の音信を
もはや理解できなくなりました
the Bible’s message.
During that long period,
there were sincere men
その長い期間のうちに—
聖書の一部を 他のいくつかの言語で
翻訳した誠実な人々がいました
that translated portions of the Bible
into some additional languages,
but these translations were,
of course, all made by hand.
しかし それらの翻訳はもちろん
すべて手書きによるものでした
Such handwritten copies of the Bible
were rare and expensive.
そうした手書きの聖書は
数が少なく高価でした
Therefore,
access to the Bible in vernacular,
ですから 自分の言語あるいは
一般の言語で読める聖書の数は—
or common languages,
was very limited.
非常に限られていました
But language was not
the only obstacle
しかし 言語だけが神の言葉の進展を脅かす
唯一の障害だったわけではありません
that threatened to prevent
the distribution of God’s Word.
Consider a second factor:
2つ目の要素があります
それは聖書の翻訳と頒布に対する
宗教指導者の直接の反対です
direct opposition
to Bible translation and distribution
from religious leaders.
That opposition
started to increase in 1229
その反対は1229年
トゥールーズの宗教会議において—
when the local church
Council of Toulouse decreed:
地元の教会が次の布告をした時から
増し加わりました
“We prohibit also
that the laity should be permitted
“我々はまた平信徒が旧約および
新約聖書を持つことを禁じる”
to have the books
of the Old or the New Testament.”
1234年にタラゴナ教会会議は
こう布告しました
In 1234,
the Council of Tarragona decreed:
“No one should possess the books
of the Old or the New Testament
“何人たりとも自国語で旧約
および新約聖書を所有してはならない”
“in the vernacular [language],
“and if anyone possesses them,
“もし所有している者がいるなら—”
“let him deliver them, within eight days
“この布告の発令から8日以内に
それらを地元の司教に提出させ—”
“from the promulgation of this decree,
“それらを焼き払うように”
to the local bishop,
so that they may be burned.”
Thus, during
a very long period in history,
こうして歴史上
非常に長い期間にわたって—
there was limited access to the Bible
一般の人々の話す言語で聖書を
読むことはほとんどできなかったのです
in the languages
spoken by common people.
But did that mean
that the Word of God
しかし それは神の言葉がずっと
存続できないという意味でしょうか？
would not continue to endure?
Neither language barriers
言語の障壁も宗教指導者たちの反対も—
nor opposition from religious leaders
神の言葉が広く知られるのを
阻止することはできませんでした
could stop God’s Word
from being made known.
Even in those dark times,
そうした暗黒時代にあっても
神の言葉を愛し それを懸命に翻訳し—
there were individuals
who loved God’s Word
and who worked hard
to translate it
人々がそれを入手できるようにした
者たちがいたのです
and to make it available to others.
Consider John Wycliffe
ジョン・ウィクリフとロラード派と
呼ばれるその追随者たちがいます
and his followers
who were called the Lollards.
John Wycliffe and his associates
ジョン・ウィクリフとその仲間たちは
1382年ごろ英訳聖書を完成しました
completed the translation
of the Bible
into English
about the year 1382.
They eagerly
hand copied the translation
翻訳した聖書の手書きの
コピーを熱心に作成し—
and then traveled
from village to village
村から村を回わり
人々に聖書を読んだのです
reading the Bible
to the common people.
Despite tremendous opposition
from the church,
教会のすさまじい反対にもかかわらず
ウィクリフと追随者たちは—
Wycliffe and his followers
made the Bible available
心の正直な多くの人々が英語で
聖書を入手できるようにしたのです
to many honesthearted people
in the English language.
After Wycliffe died in 1384,
1384年のウィクリフの死後—
その追随者たちには
厳しい反対が臨みました
great opposition
came to his followers.
Many had land
and property confiscated.
多くの者たちの土地や所有物は没収され
火あぶりにされた人もいました
Others were burned
at the stake.
In response to the work
of Wycliffe and the Lollards,
ウィクリフとロラード派の
行なったことに対応して—
in 1408,
1408年 カンタベリーの大司教であった
トマス･アランデルはこう述べました
Thomas Arundel,
Archbishop of Canterbury, declared:
“We therefore decree and ordain
“したがって我々は
次のことを布告し 定める”
“that no man shall, hereafter,
by his own authority,
“今後は何人も自らの権威で 聖書本文を
英語や他の言語に翻訳してはならない”
“translate any text of the Scripture
“into English,
or any other tongue,
. . . upon pain
of greater excommunication.”
“そうする者は破門の痛みが伴うであろう”
Did such opposition
wipe out efforts
このような反対は聖書を翻訳し広める
努力を一掃してしまったでしょうか？
to translate and make
the Bible available?
Absolutely not!
そのようなことはありません！
The work of Wycliffe
and his associates
ウィクリフと追随者たちの働きは
英国や中央ヨーロッパにおいてさえ—
stimulated interest in the Bible
throughout England
聖書への関心を高める結果となりました
and even as far as central Europe.
Religious leaders were not able
to silence the Word of God.
宗教指導者たちは神の言葉を
沈黙させることはできませんでした
In fact, within just a few decades
after Wycliffe’s death,
事実 ウィクリフの死後
わずか数十年たった後—
two factors
led to a tremendous increase
聖書が驚異的に広まるのに
役立った２つの要素が生じました
in the availability
of the Bible.
最初のものは1454年ごろに—
The first,
about the year 1454,
組み替えできる活字を用いた
印刷技術が発達したことです
was the development
of printing with movable type.
This invention would
in time allow for the printing
この発明によって多くの言語で
大量の聖書を印刷できるようになりました
of large quantities
of Bibles in many languages.
The second factor was
the compiling and printing
2番目の要素はヘブライ語および
ギリシャ語原文による聖書本文の—
of the Hebrew and Greek
original language text
収集と印刷が行なわれたことです
of the Holy Scriptures.
This allowed many translators
これにより多くの翻訳者たちは
原文で聖書本文を入手できるようになり—
to have access
to the original language texts
so that they then could produce
自分たちの言語で質の高い翻訳を
行なえるようになりました
high-quality translations
in their own languages.
What was the result?
その結果は？
In the 1500’s across Europe,
1500年代にはヨーロッパ中で
新しい翻訳が行なわれ—
fresh translations
were made and printed
一般の人々の言語で印刷されたのです
in vernacular,
or common languages,
それらは ドイツ語 英語 イタリア語
フランス語 オランダ語 チェコ語—
including German, English, Italian, French,
Dutch, Czech, Danish, Swedish,
デンマーク語 スウェーデン語—
スペイン語 スロベニア語
その他多くあります
Spanish, Slovenian, and many others.
However, opposition continued.
しかし反対は続きました
Bible translators were frequently hounded
by the Inquisition,
聖書翻訳者たちは異端審問によって
たびたび追い回され—
and some translators like
William Tyndale and John Rogers
ウィリアム・ティンダルや
ジョン・ロジャーズのように—
殺害された翻訳者たちもいます
were even put to death
for their work.
Nonetheless, the Word of God
continued to endure
にもかかわらず 神の言葉は
引き続き存続し—
and be made available
to more and more language groups.
ますます多くの言語で
入手できるようになりました
By the early 1800’s,
1800年代の初期までに
聖書翻訳は勢いを増し加えはじめました
Bible translation
began to speed up.
Bible societies
and intrepid translators
聖書協会や勇敢な翻訳者たちは
地の様々な場所で仕事を始め—
began to work
in many parts of the earth
so that the Bible began
to appear in languages
やがてアジア アフリカ
太平洋の島々の言語で—
of Asia, Africa,
the Pacific islands,
また アメリカ大陸の土着の言語でも
聖書が読めるようになりました
as well as in indigenous languages
of the Americas.
From 1800 to 1899,
1800年から1899年にかけて
聖書の一部が400の言語に翻訳され—
some portions of the Bible
were translated
into some 400 languages,
1900年から1950年にかけて
さらに500以上の言語が加えられました
and from 1900 to 1950,
more than 500 languages
were added.
Consider what has been accomplished
with the New World Translation.
「新世界訳聖書」が成し遂げたこと
について考えてみてください
As of this month,
the New World Translation
今月までに「新世界訳聖書」は—
has been produced
in whole or in part
その全部あるいは一部が
149の言語で出版され—
in 149 languages,
with an additional
37 languages approved.
さらに37の言語が承認されています
It’s obvious
that neither language barriers
それで言語の障壁も
宗教指導者の反対も—
nor opposition
from religious leaders
神の言葉の頒布を阻止できなかった
ことは明らかです
was able to stop
the distribution of God’s Word.
Jehovah has protected it
through the ages.
エホバがずっと
保護してこられたのです
It’s just as Psalm 12:6, 7 says:
それは 詩編 12編6, 7節が
述べる通りです
“The sayings of Jehovah are pure;
“エホバのみことばは浄いことば—”
“地の溶鉱炉で精錬され
七度純化された銀のようだ”
“they are like silver refined
in an earthen furnace,
“purified seven times.
“エホバよ あなたご自身が
彼らを守ってくださいます”
“You will guard them, O Jehovah;
“あなたは この世代から
定めのない時に至るまで—”
“you will protect each one of them
from this generation forever.”
“ひとりびとりを
保護してくださるのです”
Yes, Jehovah
has protected each one
そうです エホバはこの時代まで—
ご自分の語られたそれぞれの
貴重な言葉を保護してこられたのです
of his precious sayings
down through the ages.
But consider a third obstacle.
では 3つ目の障害について
考えてください
Although the Bible is now available
in whole or in part
聖書は 今やおよそ3000の言語で
全体あるいはその一部が入手できますが—
in almost 3,000 languages,
many people are no longer interested
in reading it.
多くの人はそれを読むことに無関心です
In our modern age,
people have become
現代では人々はますます懐疑的になり
宗教心がありません
increasingly skeptical and irreligious.
Scientists have extolled
the theory of evolution
科学者たちは進化論を称揚し—
and have made it appear intelligent
聡明な人なら神の存在を疑うと
思い込ませています
to doubt the existence of God.
At the same time,
同時に世の哲学は—
secular philosophy has encouraged people
自分にとって正しいと
思えるところに従って—
to make life decisions
according to what feels right to them.
人生を決定するよう人々に勧めています
What is the result?
結果はどうですか？
A world where people
are often guided
人々が自分の利己的で肉的な欲望に
導かれる世界の誕生です
by their own selfish, fleshly desires.
Instead of leading to happiness,
幸福になるどころか—
多くの人は空しくて
満足感のない状況にあります
many people are left
feeling empty and dissatisfied.
How is this third obstacle overcome?
この障害はどのように
克服されていますか？
Around the world,
世界中で 人々は神の言葉聖書を開き
自分でそれを読んでいます
people are opening
God’s Word, the Bible,
and reading it
for themselves.
それが単なる人間の知恵から出たもの
ではないことに 人々は気付いています
They’re recognizing
that its thoughts
are not simply human wisdom.
As they apply
its principles in their lives,
その原則を生活に当てはめることにより
満足と喜びを味わっています
they find
contentment and joy.
They develop
self-respect and dignity
創造者が示される正しい道徳規準
に従って生きることにより—
from living according to
the upright moral standards
自尊心と尊厳を保っています
outlined by our Creator.
As Psalm 119:97-100 states:
詩編 119編97-100節が
述べるとおりです
“How I do love your law!
“わたしはどんなにあなたの律法を
愛していることでしょう”
“I ponder over it all day long.
“それは一日じゅうわたしの
思いとなっています”
“Your commandment
makes me wiser than my enemies,
“あなたのおきてはわたしを
敵よりも賢くし—”
“それは定めのない時に至るまで
わたしのものです”
“because it is with me forever.
“I have more insight
than all my teachers,
“すべての教師に勝る
洞察力を得るようになりました”
“because I ponder over your reminders.
“あなたの諭しが
わたしの思いとなっているからです”
“I act with more understanding
than older men,
“わたしは年長者に勝る
理解力をもって行動します”
because I observe your orders.”
“あなたの命令を
守り行なったからです”
神の言葉が永久に存続することを示す
何という強力な証なのでしょう
What a powerful proof
that the Word of God endures forever.
While the advice of human philosophers
is frequently flawed,
人間の哲学者の助言には
たびたび欠陥が見つかりますが—
the Bible’s counsel works.
聖書の助言はそうではありません
If we apply it,
それを当てはめるなら—
it can help us either
to overcome or to cope
直面するかもしれない
どんな問題や状況でも—
克服したり対処したりするのに
助けとなります
with any problem
or situation that we may face.
What is more,
さらに 将来に対する神の目的が
説明されているので—
by explaining
God’s purpose for the future,
it gives us a solid hope
この地球が当初創造されたときと同じ
パラダイスに回復されるという—
this earth will be restored
to the Paradise
確かな希望を得ることができます
that it was
when it was first created.
It will be filled
with peace and righteousness.
そこには平和と義が行き渡ります
What a wonderful gift
エホバは聖書を通して 何と素晴らしい
贈り物をくださったのでしょう！
Jehovah gave us through the Bible!
そうです 言語の障壁も
宗教指導者の反対も—
Yes, languages barriers,
opposition from religious leaders,
and even
an increasingly irreligious world
増し加わる世の無関心も
神の言葉をとどめることはできません
cannot stop God’s Word.
How can you be part
of the evidence
あなたはどのようにして神の言葉が
永久に存続することの証拠を示せますか？
that the Word of God
endures forever?
Read it every day,
study it,
毎日それを読んで 学び
そこに含まれている深い考えを黙想し—
meditate on the deep thoughts
that it contains,
and then apply
those priceless teachings in your life.
計り知れない価値を持つ その教えを
生活に当てはめてください
In this way,
not just on the printed page,
そのようにして印刷されたページや
図書棚にではなく—
not just on the library shelf,
but in our minds,
in our own hearts,
わたしたちの思いと心に
また自分たちの生活において—
in our own lives
the Word of God
will truly endure forever.
神の言葉はまさに永久に
存続することになるでしょう！